<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe discouse of the merueylous victorie gotten by the king of Nauarre, against those of the holy League, on the twentieth of October 1587 Both in English, and in French as it was printed in Fraunce. Whereunto is added as soone as it came to my hand since the first impression, the true copie of a letter sent by the king of Nauarre to his secretary at Rochil, aswel in confirmation of the victorie against the Duke Ioyeuse, as also the ouerthrow that the Switzers gaue to the Duke of Guise.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1587</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02986</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855016</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855016</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20486</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02986)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20486)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 569:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe discouse of the merueylous victorie gotten by the king of Nauarre, against those of the holy League, on the twentieth of October 1587 Both in English, and in French as it was printed in Fraunce. Whereunto is added as soone as it came to my hand since the first impression, the true copie of a letter sent by the king of Nauarre to his secretary at Rochil, aswel in confirmation of the victorie against the Duke Ioyeuse, as also the ouerthrow that the Switzers gaue to the Duke of Guise.</title>
                  <author>Henry IV, King of France, 1553-1610. True copie of a letter sent by the king of Navarre to his secretary at Rochil.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe dwelling in Distaffe Lane neare the signe of the Castle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1587.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In English and French. The battle took place 21 October 1587.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Henry III, 1574-1589 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20486:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20486:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Briefe diſcourſe of the <hi>merueylous victorie gotten by the King of Nauarre, againſt thoſe of the holy League, on the twentieth of October. 1587.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Both in Engliſh, and in French</hi> as it was printed in Fraunce.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added as ſoone as it came to my hand ſince the firſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, The true copie of a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſent by the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> to his Secretary at <hi>Rochil,</hi> aſwel in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the victorie againſt the Duke <hi>Ioyeuſe,</hi> as alſo the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw that the <hi>Switzers</hi> gaue to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON <hi>Printed by Iohn Wolfe dwelling in</hi> Diſtaffe Lane neare the ſigne of the Caſtle. 1587.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="historical_account">
            <pb facs="tcp:20486:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20486:2"/>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <head>¶ A briefe diſcourſe of the meruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous victorie gotten by the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> againſt thoſe of the holy league, on the twentieth of October. 1587.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> took his way toward his Armie, being ſtraungers, by the borders of thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces which fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him moſt: and to this purpoſe, he was to paſſe the riuers of <hi>Drougne,</hi> and <hi>Lile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> had in charge to hinder the aboueſaid paſſages, notwithſtanding all daungers that might enſue, thinking, that hauing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer throwne the king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> by all likelyhoods of reaſon, the armie that was come out of <hi>Germanie,</hi> and from other places to his aide, ſhould not be able to doo anie good.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20486:3"/> with the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Soyſſon,</hi> determined reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely to paſſe the ſaid riuers. But the Duke of <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> oppoſed himſelfe to hinder them, being ſtrong, and hauing a great number of horſe-men with him, which the King of <hi>Fraunce</hi> had ſent him.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> tooke vp his lodging at <hi>Barbezieux,</hi> and afterward at <hi>Chalais:</hi> The King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> tooke his vp at <hi>Archiac:</hi> and afterward at <hi>Monlieu,</hi> and the neareſt places thereunto: both parties hauing fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to get the paſſage of the riuer of <hi>Drougne,</hi> and eſpecially the lodging of <hi>Coutras,</hi> whereas moſt conuenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they might paſſe.</p>
               <p>There paſſed manie occaſions of fighting by the way, and the King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> according to his wonted dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence got the lodging called <hi>Coutras</hi> vpon <hi>Drougne,</hi> an houre before the Duke <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> could come: Who had alreadie ſent certaine light horſe-men to take the place, who at the comming of the King left it. This was on Monday in the euening, being the nyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenth of October.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:20486:3"/>
               <p>On Tueſday next following be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the morning the Duke of <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> marched forward and encam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped himſelfe betweene the <hi>Roch Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lais</hi> &amp; <hi>Coutras,</hi> with all his armie: and pointed to fight his field halfe a league from <hi>Coutras,</hi> with the moſt vantage that might be.</p>
               <p>The king of <hi>Nauar</hi> on the otherſide of <hi>Coutras,</hi> goeth and ſetteth his men forward in battaile ray, cauſeth his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance to paſſe the riuer, the which the euening before he could not do, and cauſed them to be brought before him, and determined with all his men to bée readie to fight, whom hée found verie willing and forward. He cauſed euerie companie firſt to enter into prayer to almighty God.</p>
               <p>He appointed his armie in ſuch ſort, that all his ordinance might do him ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice without hurting any of his owne men.</p>
               <p>In ſo much that indéede his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance did that which was done to great good purpoſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Harchebuſes did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like, ſo that there was not any one part of his armie, but that got great benefit of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20486:4"/> victorie. And yet the king (by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of men) had the chiefeſt victorie of all.</p>
               <p>So that about eight of the clocke the ordinance beganne to play, and before nine of the clocke they came to handy ſtrockes. The battaile was quickly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (being a thing moſt ſtraunge by meanes of the great difference that was in the multitudes of the Duke <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> his men) ſo that at ten of the clock there was not one man amongſt the enimies that did fight. Although that in this moſt notable euerthrow as yet there appeareth not aboue twentie men loſt on the King of <hi>Nauars</hi> ſide, nor anie man of calling, or that had any gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnder him.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> was ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that graſping with the enemie endaungered himſelfe greatly. The Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> had his horſe ſtaine vnder him. The Earle of <hi>Soyſſon</hi> tooke with his owne hand diuers priſoners. The Lord of <hi>Turenes</hi> horſe was ſlaine vnder him.</p>
               <p>God who had appointed the ſucceſſe of the battaile, gaue the victorie to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20486:4"/> King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> in the which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duke <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> was ſlaine. All his chiefe men were either ſlaine or taken, except the Lord of <hi>Lauerdin,</hi> of whom as yet they know not what is become. Many aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients and ſtandards were taken, and amongſt them the chiefe ſtandard of al. The footemen all ſlaine. The ordinance taken. The carriage loſt. About thrée houres after the battaile was done, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing returned to the place where the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile was fought: they rendred great thankes vnto God. They buried the dead. They burned the lodgings of the enemy. And they did all other things that might beſéeme ſuch a notable vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie. God of his goodnes graunt that in like ſort it may continue to the benefite of this Realme.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his good ſucceſſe ſéeketh to win his aduerſaries by his great curtefie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing entreated his priſoners and ſuch as were wounded in ſuch ſort, as that they haue great cauſe to acknowledge and confeſſe that he loueth <hi>France</hi> and French men, and knoweth well how to diſcerne thoſe that are of the League.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20486:5"/> being enemies of the countrey, as hée would doo if he could, euen in the midſt of the greateſt force of the battaile.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>The names of ſuch as were ſlaine.</head>
                     <item>Monſieur de Ioyeuſe.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Sainct Sauueur <hi>his brother.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Monſieur de la Roche du Maine <hi>the yonger.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Monſieur le Comte de la Suze.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Fumel.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Rouſſay <hi>the yongeſt</hi> de Piennes guidon de Monſieur de Ioyeuſe.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Nenſuy de perigort <hi>the elder.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Monſieur le Comte de Gouallo.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur le Comte Daubijou.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Coullons <hi>brother to the</hi> Comte de la Suze.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Brize <hi>the bearer of the</hi> Cornette blanche.</item>
                     <item>Le fils du Sient de Rochefort Croyzette.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Guzacq. Cornette de Maumont.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur du Bourdet de Xaintonge <hi>ſtandard bearer of</hi> Sainct Luc.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Vaux Lieutenant de la compagnie de Monſieur de Belle-garde.</item>
                     <item>Lenſeigne du Sieur de Montigni.</item>
                     <item>Tarcelin Maiſtre de Camp.</item>
                     <item>Le Cheſnel <hi>his cheefe Capitaine.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>La Vallade <hi>one of his Captaines.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Le Capitaine Boculaud.</item>
                     <item>Le Ieune Campelz qui portoit vn drapeau.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Pleuiault.</item>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:20486:5"/>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Sainct Fort guidon de Sainct Luc.</item>
                     <item>Le Baron de Theunes.</item>
                     <item>La Brangere.</item>
                  </list> All theſe were men that had charge vnder them.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Priſoners taken, and ſome of them wounded.</head>
                     <item>Monſieur de Belle-garde <hi>taken and hurt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Monſieur de-Sainct Luc.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Sanſac.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Cypierre.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur le Marquis de Piennes.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Gautrel,</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Montigny Capitainé de la Porte.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Ville-comblin Lieutenant de Monſieur de Souuray.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Chaſteaurenard guidon du Sieur de Sanſae.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Mouuent <hi>Captaine of the light horſemen.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Monſieur le Comte de Monſoréau <hi>taken and hurt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Monſieur de la Patriere guidon de Monſieur Lauerdin.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Chaſteau-meux.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Chaſtelu.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Lauuerdiere guidon de Monſieur de la Suze. <hi>All theſe had charge vnder them.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Broeil-baudet.</item>
                  </list> And there are a great many Gentlemen wanting, and as yet not knowne.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="fre" type="version">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20486:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Diſcours, ſommaire de la Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuſe victoire, obtenue par le Roy de Nauarre, contre ceux de la Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, le vingtieſme d' Octobre. 1587.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>E Roy de Nauarre pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noit ſon chemin vers ſon armée eſtrangere par l'abord des Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces qui luy ſont fauor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables, &amp; pour ceſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect auoit à paſſer les ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uieres de Drougne, &amp; de l'Iſle.</p>
               <p>Monſier de Ioyeuſe auoit charge de luy em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſcher ce paſſage á quelque peril que ce feuſt, penſant que luy deſ-faict par vne raiſonnable conſequence, l'armée eſtrangere ne pourroit ſubſiſter.</p>
               <p>Le dict Sieur Roy, aſſiſté de Meſſeigneurs le Prince de Conde, Comte de Soyſſon, ſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoult de paſſer. Ledit Sieur de Ioyeuſe de l'em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſcher, renforſé de pluſieurs compagnies de genſ-darmes, que le Roy luy auoit enuoyées.</p>
               <p>Le dict Sieur de Ioyeuſe prend ſon logis à Barbezieux de puis à Chalays. Le Roy de Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre à Archiac. Et puis à Monlieu, &amp; lieux prochains, reſoluz tous deux de gaigner le paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage de la Drougne, &amp; ſur tout le logis de
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20486:6"/> Coutras ou elle ſe pouuoit plus commode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment paſſer.</p>
               <p>Il ſe paſſa des occaſions de combat ſur le chemin. Auſſi le Roy par ſa diligence accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumee gaigna le logis de Coutras ſur Drou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne, vne heure premier que ledit Seigneur de Ioyenſe y peuſt arriuer. Qui auoit des ja en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoye quelque cheuaux legers pour le prendre, qui le quitterent à larriuee dudict Sieur Roy. Ceſtoit le Lundy au ſoir dix-nieufieſme Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre.</p>
               <p>Le Mardy enſuiuant de grand matin Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Ioyeuſes ſe rend entre la Roche Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays &amp; Coutras, auec ſon armée. Et prend ſa place de Battaile à demyelieue de Coutras, au lieu le plus aduantageux qu'il peuſt.</p>
               <p>Le Roy de Nauarre de ſon coſté part de Coutras, &amp; luy va au deuant, met ſon armée en bataille. Faict paſſer la riuiere ſon canon, qui le ſoir pardeuant ne lauoit peu paſſer. Et le faict mener à ſa teſte. Reſoult tous les ſiens à ce combat, qu'il trouua pleins dardeur &amp; deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Faict faire la priere à Dieu de troupe en troupe.</p>
               <p>Diſpoſe au reſte ſon armée en telle ſorte, que toutes les pieces ſeruirent, &amp; pouuoyent faire leur effort, ſans incommoder ni les vns, ni les autres des ſiens.</p>
               <p>Comme de faict ſon artillerie joua fort à propos, l'arquebouſerie de meſme, &amp; ny heut partie de ſon armée qui n'euſt notable part de la victoire. Bien que certes ſa Majeſté (au juge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment de tous) heuſt la principalle.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:20486:7"/>
               <p>Tanty a que ſur les huict heures l'artillerie commença a iouer, &amp; auant neuf heures on vint aux mains. Fut la bataille ſi toſt decidée, (Choſe eſtrange en legalite de toutes forces,) qu'a dix heures il ny auoit homme de l'enne mi qui rendiſt combat, meſme qui feuſt en veue, Sans touteſ-fois qu'il ſe ſoyt perdu en vne ſi notable deſ-faicte (qui paroiſſe encore) vingt hommes ſoyt de pied, ſoyt de Cheual du coſte dudict Sieur Roy de Nauarre, ny meſme pas vn de marque, ou homme de commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Le Roy de Nauarre eſt venu aux main<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> juſques à Colleter. Monſieur le Prince, ſon Cheual tué. Monſieur le Prince de Soyſſons y à faict des priſonniers de ſa main, Monſieur d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Turene ſon cheual tué.</p>
               <p>Dieu qui à ordonné l'iſſue des Batailles, a donné la victoire au prince, en laquelle Mon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſieur de Ioyeuſe à eſté tué. Tous les chefz ou mortz ou prins, reſerué le Sieur de Lauer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> din, qu'on ne ſçait encores qu'il eſt deuenu<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Les inſeignes &amp; cornettes priſes, meſmes la generalle. L'infanterie toute deſ-faicte, L<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> canon prins, Le Bagage perdu. La victoir<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuyuie trois heures ou plus. Laction de grace faicte à Dieu au retour au champ de la Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taille. Les mortz enterrez. Les logis de l'en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemi bruſlez. Et tout ce en ſomme qui peu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appartenir aux circonſtances d'vne ſignale<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> victoire, Que Dieu luy doint pourſuyure au bien &amp; eſtat de ce Royaume.</p>
               <p>Le Roy de Nauarre les à voulu vaincr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:20486:7"/> encores en courtoyſie, ayant tellement tracté les prinſonniers, &amp; les bleſſez qu'ils ont tous dequoy cognoiſtre, q'uil ayme la France &amp; les Françoys, &amp; les ſçayt bien diſcerner dauec ceulx de la Ligue ennemis de l'eſtat, comme <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> feroit s'il pouuoit dans le ſort des armes.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>MORTS.</head>
                     <item>Monſieur de Ioyeuſe.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Sainct Sauueur ſon frere.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de la Roche du Maine le Ieune.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur le Comte de la Suze.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Fumel.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Rouſſay puiſné de Piennes gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don de Monſieur de Ioyeuſe.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Nenfuy de perigort laiſné.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur le Comte de Gouallo.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur le Comte Daubijou.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Coullons frere du Comte de la Suze.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Brize qui portoit la Cornette blanche.</item>
                     <item>Le fils du Sieur de Rochefort Croyzette.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Guzacq. Cornette de Maumont.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur du Bourdet de zaintonge enſeigne de Sainct Luc.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Vaux Lieutenant de la compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnie de Monſleur de Belle-garde.</item>
                     <item>Len ſeigne du Sieur de Montigni.</item>
                     <item>Tarcelin Maiſtre de Camp.</item>
                     <item>Le Cheſnel ſon premier Capitaine.</item>
                     <item>La Vallade l'vn de ſes Capitaines.</item>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:20486:8"/>
                     <item>Le Cappitaine Boculaud.</item>
                     <item>Le Ieune Campelz qui portoit vn drapeau.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Pleuiault.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Sainct Fort guidon de Sainct Luc.</item>
                     <item>Le Baron de Theunes.</item>
                     <item>La Brangere.</item>
                  </list> Tous ayans charge en l'armée.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Priſonniers &amp; Bleſſez.</head>
                     <item>Monſieur de Belle-garde pris &amp; bleſſé.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Sainct Luc.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Sanſac.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Cypierre.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur le Marquis de Piennes.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Gautrel.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Montigny Capitainé de la Porte</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Ville-comblin Lieutenant de Monſieur de Souuray.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Chaſteaurenard guidon du Sieu de Sanſac.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Mouuent Capitaine de cheuau legers.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur le Comte de Monſoréau pris &amp; bleſſe.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de la Patriere guidon de Monſieur Lauerdin.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Chaſteau-meux.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Chaſtelu.</item>
                     <item>Monſieur de Lauuerdiere guidon de Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſieu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> de la Suze, tous ayans charge.</item>
                     <item>Le Sieur de Broeil-baudet.</item>
                  </list> Et pluſieurs autre gentils-hommes non encore recognus.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20486:8"/>
            <head>The true copie of a Letter written and ſent by the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent King of Nauarre, to his Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie of eſtate, Monſieur de la Marcilliare after the battel lately had at Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Arcilliare</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch <hi>Pomenia</hi> vnto you, to let the maiſters of <hi>Rochel</hi> to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand of the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie &amp; abſolute vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie which God hath giuen me, in the which battell the generall of the enimies armie is ſlaine, and with him almoſt all the Cheeſtains and Capteins are likewiſe either ſlaine or taken. The great Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, Artillerie, Cornets and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, both of horſemen and footemen are taken, with a generall diſſipation of the whole Armie, for the which it is duetifull that in publike and priuate ſorte, wee render thankes to almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20486:9"/> God. I pray you further the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſupply: for we muſt goe to mete our <hi>Roytors,</hi> who for their part haue giuen an ouerthrow to ſome part of the Duke of <hi>Gwyſe</hi> his armie, which now dareth not ſcarſely to ſhew himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more before them, but keepeth him ſelfe aloofe in the backe of the forces, to giue the looking on. You ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo haue an eye to the performance of my orders and commandements, and to that which may concerne my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. And ſo I pray God to keepe you in his ſafegarde.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Countrace</hi> 
                  <date>this xxi. of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. 1587.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Your moſt louing M. Henry.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20486:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
